JAHRESZEIT HOTEL (FRANKFURT)
JAHRESZEIT OTEL (FRANKFURT)
The experiments… of the Red Rose Mansion are…
Kırmızı Güllü Malikâne'deki deneyler
still happening.
hâlâ devam ediyor.
And that devil… he's got himself an apprentice now.
Ve o iblis kendine bir çırak buldu.
The guy with glasses.
Gözlüklü adam.
The survivor of… the Red Rose Mansion…
Kırmızı Güllü Malikâne'den sağ çıkan adam.
Petr Čapek.
Petr Čapek.
That guy… he's trying to control the devil.
O adam iblisi kontrol etmeye çalışıyor
Follow that car.
Şu arabayı takip et.
He's getting away!
Kaçıyor!
Where…
Nerede…
Where am I?
Neredeyim ben?
Are you conscious now?
Bilincin açıldı mı?
How are you feeling?
-Nasıl hissediyorsun? -İyi.
You're lucky. All you got was a sprained ankle.
Şanslısın, sadece ayak bileğini burktun.
I checked your head, but I don't think you hit it hard.
Başına baktım, sertçe vurduğunu sanmıyorum.
But I'm not a specialist like you.
Gerçi ben senin gibi uzman değilim.
How do you know me?
-Beni nereden tanıyorsun? -Yetenekli beyin cerrahı Dr. Tenma'sın.
I read about you in the paper.
-Gazetede hakkında yazı okudum. -Sen kimsin?
I'm a dentist around here. I'm Milan Kolasch.
Buralarda bir dişçiyim. Ben Milan Kolasch.
I just happened to pass by after you were hit by that car.
O araba sana çarptığında şans eseri oradan geçiyordum.
The driver got the heck out of there fast.
Araba sürücüsü anında basıp gitti.
You should stay in bed some more.
Biraz daha yatakta kal.
No. I'll only cause you trouble.
Hayır, başına bela açarım.
Letting you walk out of here on that leg
Bacağın böyleyken buradan gitmene izin verirsem,
and getting snatched by the cops around here would be even bigger trouble.
ve polis seni buralarda yakalarsa başıma daha büyük bela açarsın.
Around here?
Buralarda mı?
This is the Turkish Quarter of Frankfurt.
-Frankfurt'taki Türk Mahallesi'ndeyiz. -Türk Mahallesi mi?
It's more like this used to be the Turkish Quarter.
Eskiden Türk Mahallesi'ydi, demek daha doğru olur.
They're tearing down everything in the name of redevelopment.
Kentsel dönüşüm adı altında her şeyi yıkıyorlar.
Nearly all the Turks around here have moved elsewhere.
Buradaki neredeyse her Türk başka bir yere taşındı.
Before, when the right-wing extremists tried to burn this place down,
Daha önce aşırı sağcılar burayı yakmaya çalıştığında
we banded together to fight them off.
el ele verip onlara kafa tuttuk.
Is the Bahir Cafe also gone?
Bahir Kafe de gitti mi?
Yes. It disappeared long ago.
Evet, gideli uzun zaman oldu.
Do you know this neighborhood?
Bu mahalleyi biliyor musun?
Yes, a little.
Evet, biraz.
Anyway, if you can stand, why not eat with us there?
Neyse, ayağa kalkabilirsen bizimle içeride yemek yesene.
Food's better when it's shared.
Yemek paylaşılınca güzeldir.
Today, it's Vietnamese food.
Bugün Vietnam yemeği yiyoruz.
Minh made it.
Minh yaptı.
There's pho ga and cha gio tom.
Pho ga ve cha gio tom var.
Minh's Vietnamese dishes are the best.
Minh'in Vietnam yemekleri gibisi yoktur.
Help yourself to all you like.
İstediğini ye.
It's delicious.
Enfes olmuş.
I love pork, but the Turks' religion forbids eating it.
Domuz etini çok severim
We don't get much Czech food.
Çek yemeği de çok yemiyoruz.
That's because Milan is a terrible cook.
Milan'ın yemekleri çok kötü de ondan.
I'm sorry.
Özür dilerim.
Everyone takes turns making dishes from their own country.
Herkes sırayla kendi ülkesinin yemeğini yapıyor.
It's a luxury being able to enjoy food from different countries every day.
Her gün farklı ülkenin yemeğini yemek büyük bir lüks.
You're Japanese, right, Dr. Tenma?
Japon'sunuz, değil mi Dr. Tenma?
What kind of Japanese food is there?
Ne gibi Japon yemekleri var?
Japanese food?
Japon yemekleri mi?
I know! Why don't you cook us some next time?
Buldum, bir dahaki sefere bize yemek yapsana.
I can hardly wait!
Merakla bekliyorum!
Let's see. There's pork in katsudon.
Bir düşüneyim, katsudon'da domuz eti var.
And sushi… Some people don't like raw fish.
Suşi… Kimileri çiğ yemek sevmez.
How about oyakodon?
Oyakodon nasıl olur?
Oyakodon?
Oyakodon mu?
Yes. It's rice topped with chicken and eggs mixed with a sauce.
Evet, üzerinde tavuk ve yumurta olan soslu pirinç.
Why's it called oyakodon?
Adı neden oyakodon?
Oya is "parent," and ko is "child." Don means "bowl."
"Oya" ebeveyn, "ko" çocuk, "don" da kâse demek.
So it's "parent and child bowl"?
Yani ebeveyn, çocuk kâsesi mi?
Japanese cooking sure has a funny sense of humor.
Japon yemeklerinin kesinlikle mizahi yönü varmış.
The chicken and egg are the parent and child!
Tavukla yumurta ebeveyn ve çocuk oluyor.
What's the matter, Tenma?
Ne oldu Tenma?
Nothing.
Hiç.
Don't you like the food?
Yemeği mi sevmedin?
No. It's delicious.
Hayır, enfes olmuş.
It's been such a long time
Böyle güzel bir yemek yemeyeli
since I had such good food…
ve böyle hoş bir sofraya oturmayalı
and such a pleasant meal.
uzun zaman oldu sadece.
Good night, Tenma.
İyi geceler Tenma.
Good night.
İyi geceler.
I wonder how long it will take before I can walk.
Ne kadar süre içinde yürüyebileceğim acaba?
I don't have time to lie around here.
Yatıp bekleyecek vaktim yok.
Petr… Čapek…
Petr Čapek.
A gun.
Silah.
A report on Petr Čapek's movements.
Petr Čapek'in gittiği yerler hakkında rapor.
It must have seemed strange to you.
Sana tuhaf gelmiş olmalı.
The cops showed up so quickly not because they were after you.
Polislerin birden ortaya çıkma sebepleri
The cops were watching him to protect him from me.
Polisler onu benden korumak için izliyordu.
I'm going to kill Petr Čapek.
Petr Čapek'i öldüreceğim.
It's no good.
Yok, olmuyor.
That's odd.
Tuhaf.
I used to be able to make ones that flew far.
Eskiden uzağa uçabilen uçaklar yapabilirdim.
Milan's good at making paper airplanes.
Milan kâğıttan uçak yapmakta iyi.
They fly all the way over those roofs over there.
Şuradaki çatıların üzerilerinden uçabiliyorlar.
Is that right?
Öyle mi?
Do you know what Milan always says?
Milan hep ne der bilir misin?
He made us a promise.
Bize bir söz verdi.
We're going to go even farther than just those roofs.
O çatılardan bile uzağa uçacağız.
We'll go to Turkey and Vietnam, and even the Czech Republic.
Türkiye'ye, Vietnam'a, hatta Çek Cumhuriyeti'ne gideceğiz.
We'll visit all our countries together.
Hepimizin ülkesini birlikte gezeceğiz.
-Right? -Yes.
-Değil mi? -Evet.
Fly!
Uç!
It's still not good.
Hâlâ olmuyor.
-Why won't it fly? -I wonder why.
-Neden uçmuyor? -Kim bilir?
I'm going to kill Petr Čapek.
Petr Čapek'i öldüreceğim.
Why are you going to do that, Milan?
Neden öldüreceksin Milan?
That guy… That Petr Čapek is…
O adam, Petr Čapek denen o adam
a devil.
bir iblis.
In 1989, the night before
1989 senesinde, Çekoslovakya Komünist Partisi'nin
he escaped to this country.
bu ülkeye kaçtı.
After he moved here to Frankfurt, he started a school teaching German.
Frankfurt'a kaçtıktan sonra Almanca kursu açtı.
He was a very quiet man.
Çok sessiz bir adamdı
But after a while, a change came over the children.
ama bir süre sonra çocuklarda bir değişiklik görüldü.
The children from his school started killing themselves.
Kursundaki çocuklar kendilerini öldürmeye başladı.
Then they started to become extremely violent.
Sonra şiddete çok eğilimli olmaya başladılar.
Then one day, there was a riot
Sonra bir gün bir isyan çıktı.
that was nothing less than child-on-child murder.
O isyanda çocuklar birbirini öldürdü.
I interviewed the child who was the leader of the incident when he was in custody.
Olayın lideri olan çocuk gözaltındayken onunla görüştüm.
This is what he told me.
Bana şöyle dedi,
"I want to go back to the book readings."
"Kitap okuma etkinliklerine dönmek istiyorum"
Book readings?
Kitap okuma mı?
That night, while in custody, the boy killed himself.
Çocuk o gece gözaltındayken kendini öldürdü.
He was my son.
O çocuk benim oğlumdu.
In the uproar, Čapek left the city and disappeared.
Curcunada Čapek şehirden ayrılıp ortadan kayboldu.
The next time he showed up here,
Buraya bir sonraki gelişinde
he was like a different person.
farklı bir insana dönüşmüştü.
He led a Frankfurt underground organization
Frankfurt'ta bir yeraltı örgütünü yönetiyordu
Then he began to drive out Turks and other foreigners from the city.
Sonra Türkleri ve diğer yabancıları şehirden kovmaya başladı.
I don't know what he's trying to do with this city.
Bu şehirde ne yapmaya çalıştığını bilmiyorum
But their violence reached its peak
ama 1996'da Türk Mahallesi'ni yakmaya çalıştıklarında
when they tried to burn down the Turkish Quarter in 1996.
şiddete eğilimleri hat safhaya çıkmıştı.
You know about that incident, don't you?
O olayı biliyorsun, değil mi?
Yes. I saw it on the news.
Evet, haberlerde görmüştüm.
The people in this neighborhood formed a vigilante group to resist them.
Bu mahalledeki insanlar onlara karşı koymak için bir grup kurdu
But in a mere three months, the five leaders
ama sadece üç ay içinde o grubun beş lideri
of the vigilante group
açıklaması olmayan olaylarda birer birer öldü.
And those five dead people are…
O ölen beş kişi de…
Suleiman's son, Tung's father, Minh's husband,
Süleyman'ın oğlu, Tung'un babası, Minh'in kocası,
Mustafa's son, and Shemel's father.
Mustafa'nın oğlu, Shemel'in babası.
They didn't just die.
Sıradan bir ölüm değildi.
They were murdered…
Onları
by Petr Čapek.
Petr Čapek öldürdü.
I don't know why you were watching Čapek.
Čapek'i neden takip ettiğini bilmiyorum
But I'll tell you one thing.
ama sana şunu söyleyeyim,
I will be the person who kills Čapek.
Čapek'in ölümü benim elimden olacak.
Just you watch.
Seyredin.
I think this next one will do well.
Şimdi yapacağım olacak.
No way.
-Mümkün değil. -Hayır, buna çok uğraştım.
No matter how hard you try, some things are just impossible.
Ne kadar uğraşırsan uğraş bazı şeyler imkânsızdır.
We already know that.
Bunu zaten biliyoruz.
We know that all of us traveling to Turkey or Vietnam is impossible.
Birlikte Türkiye'ye veya Vietnam'a gitmemizin
I'm just fine living here
Milan ve Tung'la burada yaşamaktan memnunum.
Yes!
Evet.
Okay, it's done.
Tamam, işte oldu. Bu uçak kesinlikle uçacak.
Fly.
Uç.
See?
Gördün mü?
You did it! It's flying!
Başardın! Uçuyor!
Amazing! Look at it go!
Harika, nasıl da uçuyor.
I'm not sure I can get it to fly over the roofs like Milan's.
Milan'ın uçağı gibi çatıların üzerinden uçmasını sağlayamam
But I still got it to fly.
ama yine de uçurdum.
Aren't you glad we didn't give up?
Pes etmemek iyi olmadı mı?
-Yes!
-Evet!
Don't ever give up.
Asla pes etmeyin.
Where's my gun?
Silahım nerede?
What did you do with my gun that was in that drawer?
Çekmecedeki silahımı ne yaptın?
My chance to shoot Čapek is here. I'm going now to do it.
Čapek'i vurmak için elime fırsat geçti. Şimdi vuracağım.
Give me back my gun.
Silahımı geri ver.
I can't let you do that.
Bunu yapmana izin veremem.
I can't give you your gun.
Sana silahını veremem.
This is the gun that was in your coat.
Bu silah ceketindeydi.
When I do this, I want to use the gun I've trained with.
Onu çalıştığım silahla vurmak istiyorum.
Now, will you give me my gun?
Silahımı verecek misin?
You have a family now.
Artık bir ailen var.
You shouldn't do this.
Bunu yapmamalısın.
I've been watching Čapek's movements for a very long time.
Uzun zamandır Čapek'in nereye gittiğini izliyorum.
There's no better chance to kill him than today.
Onu öldürmem için en iyi fırsat bugün.
Please.
Lütfen.
Don't do this, Milan.
Bunu yapma Milan.
Didn't I make myself clear? Don't interfere.
Açıkça belirtmedim mi? Karışma.
Even if you get vengeance now, the dead won't come back.
İntikamını alsan bile ölen insanlar geri gelmeyecek.
What's more, think about the future.
Dahası, geleceğini düşün.
You have no right to talk to me like that.
Benimle böyle konuşmaya hakkın yok.
Milan…
Milan…
You and I are the same, Dr. Tenma.
İkimiz aynıyız Dr. Tenma.
I looked into you.
Seni araştırdım.
If what you claim is true,
Söylediklerin doğruysa
what you and I are trying to do is the same.
seninle aynı şeyi yapmaya çalışıyoruz.
He didn't use to be that way.
Eskiden böyle biri değildi.
The Čapek I knew…
Benim tanıdığım Čapek
wasn't the devil he's become!
şu anki gibi bir iblis değildi.
Petr Čapek and I were childhood friends!
Petr Čapek'le çocukluk arkadaşıydık.
I'm the one who invited him to this country!
Onu bu ülkeye ben davet ettim!
What do you think is on the other side of the border?
Sınırın diğer tarafında sence ne var?
We're not supposed to go there.
Oraya gitmememiz gerek.
I know we're not supposed to go there.
Gitmememiz gerektiğini biliyorum.
But haven't you heard?
Ama duymadın mı?
It's a wonderful place on the other side of the border.
Sınırın öbür ucu harika bir yermiş.
They have cities that are lit up all night.
Gece boyu ışıl ışıl olan şehirler varmış.
Are you sure, Petr? Who told you that?
Emin misin Petr? Bunu kim söyledi?
Old Man Gregor did.
İhtiyar Gregor söyledi.
That guy's an alcoholic.
O adam alkoliğin teki.
Besides, I've heard there is something
Ayrıca sınırın öbür ucunda insanları mahveden bir şey varmış,
Something that ruins people, huh?
İnsanları mahveden bir şey mi?
I'd like to see that.
Onu görmeyi çok isterim.
Why would you want to see that?
Onu neden görmek isteyesin ki?
Fly!
Uç!
It's caught the wind!
Rüzgârı yakaladı!
You're good, Milan!
Çok iyisin Milan.
Look at it fly!
Nasıl da uçuyor.
Wow! That one's going to cross the border!
Vay canına! Bu uçak, sınırı geçecek!
Go take a look for us!
Bizim için git bir bak.
We grew up in a town near the Czechoslovakia-Austrian border.
Çekoslovakya Avusturya sınırı yakınında bir şehirde büyüdük.
Mine was a blue-collar family, his was a white-collar one.
Benim ailem mavi yakalı, onunkiler beyaz yakalıydı
But for some strange reason, we got along together.
ama her nedense iyi anlaştık.
In 1989, when the Czechoslovakia Communist Party collapsed,
1989 yılında Çekoslovakya Komünist Partisi çöktüğünde
I was the one who helped him defect.
iltica etmesine ben yardım ettim.
The one who invited that devil to this country…
O iblisi bu ülkeye davet eden
was me.
bendim.
PRAGUE,1969
PRAG, 1969
I was worried about you when the Soviet Army invaded last year.
Sovyet Ordusu geçen sene işgal edildiğinde senin için endişelendim.
Several people I knew were taken away.
Birkaç tanıdığım götürüldü
But I was safe and am still here. How are you doing?
ama ben güvendeydim, hâlâ güvendeyim. Sen nasılsın?
Me?
Ben mi?
I'm making it by somehow as a fledgling dentist.
Çaylak bir dişçi olarak bir şekilde idare ediyorum.
A dentist, huh?
Dişçisin demek.
You were always good with your hands.
Ellerini kullanmakta hep çok iyiydin.
I wish I were as good as you at getting ahead in the world.
İleri gidebilmekte keşke senin kadar başarılı olsam.
Yes, I probably only still have my current position after the Soviets came
Evet, Sovyetlerin dağılmasından sonra mevcut konumumu korumamı
because of my skill at making my way in the world.
muhtemelen ilerleme başarıma borçluyum.
I had a lot of fun during "The Prague Spring."
"Prag Baharı" sırasında çok eğlendim.
I even went to the West.
Batı'ya bile gittim.
When we were kids, we often talked about what kind of place the other side was.
Çocukken öteki tarafın nasıl bir yer olduğunu konuşurduk hep.
Did you find out?
Öğrendin mi?
I sure did.
Öğrendim tabii.
And?
Nasılmış peki?
There was nothing. There's nothing neither here nor there.
Hiçbir şey yok. Burada da orada da hiçbir şey yok.
This country is broken.
Bu ülkenin çivisi çıkmış
But the countries over there aren't any better.
ama oradaki ülkeler de iyi değil.
I see.
Anlıyorum.
You said I'm good at getting ahead in the world.
Dünyada ilerleme konusunda iyi olduğumu söyledin.
I met someone recently who wants to use those skills of mine.
Bu yeteneklerimi kullanmak isteyen biriyle tanıştım.
Really?
Gerçekten mi?
This guy's so amazing
Harika bir adam.
that after meeting him, my current status means nothing to me anymore.
Onunla tanıştıktan sonra mevcut konumum benim için
Even though I believe that this country
Bu ülkenin ve öteki taraftakilerin
and those on the other side have nothing to offer,
bana bir şey veremeyeceğini düşünsem de
he's given me completely new hope.
o adam bana yepyeni bir umut aşıladı.
He's someone who can create something completely new.
Yepyeni bir şey yaratabilen birisi o.
So, what does this guy create?
Bu adam ne yarattı peki?
What does he create? Let's see…
Ne mi yarattı? Bir düşüneyim.
It might be something rather frightening.
Biraz ürkütücü kaçabilir.
When I look back on it now,
Şimdi dönüp baktığımda
something inside him must have started to break then.
içinde bir şeyler o zaman kırılmaya başlamıştı.
Give me back my gun.
Silahımı geri ver.
Here, you can have your gun back.
Al, silahını geri alabilirsin.
Don't do it, Milan.
Yapma Milan.
You shouldn't do this.
Bunu yapma.
There's no point in stopping me. I will kill him.
Beni durdurmaya çalışman anlamsız. Onu öldüreceğim.
But you're surrounded by a family now.
Ama artık bir ailen var.
He's the one who murdered their families.
Onların ailelerini o öldürdü.
I'm the one who brought him to this country
Onu bu ülkeye getiren benim. Hepsinin ailesini buraya gelince öldürdü.
And… he killed my son too.
Oğlumu da öldürdü.
When they tried to burn down this neighborhood,
Bu mahalleyi yakmaya çalıştıklarında
there was someone here who the Turks still talk about.
Türklerin şu an bile hakkında konuştuğu birisi vardı.
He was a Japanese man who rushed around
Oradan oraya koşup yaralılarla ilgilenen
caring for the wounded and trying to put out the fires.
ve yangınları söndürmeye çalışan Japon bir adamdı.
It was you, wasn't it, Dr. Tenma?
O kişi sendin, değil mi Dr. Tenma?
I believe you.
Sana inanıyorum.
I understand very well what you're trying to do.
Ne yapmaya çalıştığını çok iyi anlıyorum.
You and I are the same.
İkimiz eşitiz.
I'm going. It's time.
Ben gidiyorum, vakit geldi.
If I miss this chance, I doubt I'll get another one.
Bu şansı kaçırırsam elime başka bir şans geçmez.
Milan!
Milan.
Thank you for trying to stop me.
Beni durdurmaya çalıştığın için teşekkürler.
If I were in your shoes,
Senin yerinde olsaydım
I don't think I could stop myself either.
ben de kendimi durduramazdım.
ADMISSION TICKET MILAN KOLASCH
GİRİŞ BİLETİ
-What? -Oh my God!
-Ne? -Aman tanrım!
This is good!
Çok güzel.
Yes. This is delicious.
Evet, enfes olmuş.
This Japanese oyakodon is good!
Oyakodon adlı bu Japon yemeği lezizmiş.
-Yes! -Indeed!
-Evet. -Aynen.
Is your leg all right?
Bacağın iyi mi?
Would you like me to help, Dr. Tenma?
Yardım ister misin Dr. Tenma?
No. Yours is almost ready, Minh.
Hayır, yemeğin neredeyse hazır Minh.
Milan sure is late.
Milan çok geç kaldı.
I'm sure he'll be home soon.
Eminim birazdan gelir.
Yes. It tastes better freshly made, so I'll make Milan's later.
Evet, sıcak yapılınca daha güzel olur. Milan'ınkini sonra yaparım.
Really? Okay then.
Cidden mi? Peki o zaman.
…at the Roedelheim Convention Center in Frankfurt,
…Frankfurt'ta Roedelheim Fuar Merkezi'nde
a man with a handgun opened fire.
silahlı bir adam ateş açtı.
The gunman was shot and killed
Silahlı saldırgan
by police providing security at the convention.
fuardaki polisler tarafından vurularak öldürüldü.
No other casualties were reported.
Başka bir yaralı yok.
The center was thrown into panic since many attendees
Katılımcılar panik içinde kaldı. Çoğu yurt dışından gelen önemli kişilerdi.
The gunman's identity and motives are still unknown at this time.
Silahlı saldırganın kimliği ve saldırma sebebi henüz bilinmiyor.
We'll now show footage of the incident taken by…
Şimdi olayın görüntüsünü sizlere…
Everyone loves it! They say it's great.
Herkes bayıldı. Harika olmuş diyorlar.
I sure hope Milan gets back soon to have it.
Umarım Milan birazdan gelir de yer.
Here is footage of the incident.
Olayın görüntüsünü veriyoruz.
That man…
O adam…
He's the one from the Red Rose Mansion…
O adam Kırmızı Güllü Malikâne'den…
Keeping secrets from him is a no-no.
Ondan sır saklamak büyük ayıp.
Subtitle translation by: Brian Athey
Alt yazı çevirmeni: Ömür Gencer